Guide to the Charles William Shepherd archive of voyages to Iceland, circa 1844-1890.
Shepherd, Charles William archive of voyages to Iceland
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Charles William Shepherd archive of voyages to Iceland, circa 1844-1890.
6869
1 cubic foot.
Manuscripts
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Manuscripts relating to travels to Iceland.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
The collection includes a field journal, two fair-copy journals, an annotated 1844 map of Iceland, several proof sections of Shepherd's The North-West Peninsula of Iceland (1867) and a copy of the published book. It also includes correspondence and newspaper clippings.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Fowler, G. G.; Shepherd, Charles William.; Shepherd, Charles William.; Upcher, H. M.; Fiske Icelandic Collection.
Subjects:
Bird watching -- Iceland.; Bird watching; Travel
Places:
Iceland -- Description and travel.; Iceland
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Correspondence
Series II. Newspaper Book Reviews
Series III. Bound Manuscripts
Series iV. Additional Material
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Correspondence
  - Miscellaneous Notes, Undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Notes or a portion of a letter, undecipherable addressee and writer, mention of Reykjavik.
  - Supplies expenses, Undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Financial documents listing objects)
  - Supply expense ledger, May 1, 1862; 3 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Financial document listing objects (such as paper and whisky)
  - Letter from C. W. Shepherd to “My dear Father”, May 4, 1862; 4 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Addressed from Reyk[j]avik. Mentions traveling.
  - Letter from C. W. Shepherd to “My dear Father”, May 5, 1862; 5 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Mentions leaving from Reyk[j]avik that morning and traveling in Iceland.
  - Letter from C. W. Shepherd to “My dear Father”, May, 25, 1862; 6 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Addressed from Thingnefs. Mentions the rain and snow of Iceland, continues discussion of travel.
  - Letter "Accepted by Mr. Shepherd", May 28, 1862; 7 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Mentions finances.
  - Letter from James Retcher to "My dear Shepherd", August 25, 1862; 8 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Addressed from Peterhead (presumably Scotland). Mentions a hurried message and difficulties with the post and travel.
  - Letter from O. V. Gislason to "My dear friend", April 24, 1864; 9 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Addressed from Iceland. Mentions working on translating texts into Icelandic, asks for assistance to travel to England.
  - Letter from the Royal Geographical Society, March 19, 1867; 10 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Documents the receiving of The North-West Peninsula of Iceland and giving thanks for its donation to the Society.
  - Letter from the Zoological Society of London, March 21, 1867; 11 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gives thanks for the gift of The North-West Peninsula of Iceland to the library.
  - Letter from W. M. James to “My dear Shepherd", April 9, 1868; 12 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Addressed from Fürstenbad. Discusses Shepherd’s book (The North-West Peninsula of Iceland).
  - Letter to Cheriton Bickley Kent from Kenny Mac Cormac, July 21, 1870; 13 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Discusses welding and mentions working in Iceland.
- Series II. Newspaper Book Reviews
  - The Morning Star, February 6, 1863 (Mapcase-folder 1)
    Contains advertisements, railway traffics, weather report, shipping intelligence, police and law intelligence.
  - Maidstone Telegraph No. 419, December 15, 1866 (Mapcase-folder 1)
    Samples of articles and topics: railway times, London markets, “Coroner’s Inquiet,” assorted advertisements, articles on trade unions, articles on education, police brutality, “The Paris Exhibition,” “Death of a Vegetarian from Abstemiousness, “Discovery of a Skeleton in Ratcliffe Highway.”
  - The Athenaeum: Journal of English and Foreign Literature, Science, and the Fine Arts, London, March 9, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Among many others, contains a review of The North-West Peninsula of Iceland.
  - Land and Water Vol. 3 No. 60, March 16, 1867 (Mapcase-folder 1)
  - The Globe and Traveller No. 21, 407, Evening, March 11, 1867 (Mapcase-folder 1)
  - Gardeners Chronicle, March 16, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Review of The North-West Peninsula of Iceland.
  - Morning Herald, April 4, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - London Review, April 6, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Spectator, April 20, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Review of The St. Stephen’s Chronicle, The Sorrows of Hypsipyle, The Wife’s Litany and Other Pieces in Verse, A Dictionary of Photography, Sunshine and Showers, Prose Works of John Greenleaf Whittier, Germany from the Baltic to the Adriatic; or Prussia, Austria, and Venetia, with Reference to the Late War, The North-West Peninsula of Iceland, being the Journal of a Tour in Iceland in the Spring and Summer of 1862, The Law of Libel, as Affecting the Newspaper Press, with proposed Amendments, The Aeneis of Virgil, Zaida’s Nursery Notebook, for the Use of Mothers, Pity, Man: A Story of Light and Darkness, Practical Housekeeping, or the Duties of a Homewife, Maxon’s Standard Penny Readings, Africa. Prussia, How to Study the New Testament, and Dan’s Treasure; or, Labour and Love.
  - Daily News, April 27, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Birmingham Daily Gazette Vol. 9 No. 1290, April 29, 1867 (Mapcase-folder 1)
  - Lancet, May 11, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Pall Mall Gazette: An Evening Newspaper and Review, May 30, 1867 (Mapcase-folder 1)
  - The Times, June 6, 1867 (Mapcase-folder 1)
- Series III. Bound Manuscripts
  - Travel Journal of C. W. Shepherd, April 19, 1862 - June 27, 1862; 14 (Box 1)
    Rough travel itinerary on first page from April 19th to the end of June; writing begins May 2, ends Friday, June 27; 116 pages of writing.
  - Travel journal of H. M. Upchev, April 19, 1862 - July 30, 1862; 15 (Box 1)
    Black cover. Has rough itineraries from April to August (writing appears to be from April to July); begins with April 19, 1862; has a plant stuck between its last few pages.
  - Small black notepad, April 28, 1862 - July 29, 1862; 16 (Box 1)
    Includes advertisement for the 1862 Royal Mail Steam Ship from Reykjavik to Copenhagen; starting in April, very faded notes on travel (including weather); continues to July; Jack Shepherd written on back cover.
  - Journal with red cover, July 17 186? - October 3, 186??; 17 (Box 1)
    Front inside cover has a rudimentary travel itinerary for July and August; back inside cover continues to September and up until October 3; 123 written pages; begins with leaving London on July 17 ,ends with September 3 with what should be Mývatn based on the itinerary; the journal records details of travel and the landscapes.
  - Small black wallet/purse with writings, 18 (Box 1)
    Only fragmentary papers (baggage ticket from Marseilles, some papers with names, Shepherd is mentioned).
- Series iV. Additional Material
  - The North-West Peninsula of Iceland: Being the Journal of a Tour in Iceland in the Spring and Summer of 1862, 1867; 19 (Box 1)
    By C. W. Shepherd, M.A., F.Z.S., published in London 1867 by Longmans, Green, and Co.; has a green cover.
  - Pages from The North-West Peninsula of Iceland, 1867; 20 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Goða-Foss painting (Mapcase-folder 1)
    1A - Rendering of landscape featuring waterfalls and mountains, two figures perched to the top left
  - Ísa-Fjörðr Town painting (Mapcase-folder 1)
    1B - Depicts a stretch of land cutting across a fjord; three boats to the right, several small houses on the land-bridge
  - Uppdráttr Íslands (Carte d‘Islande) by Olafs Nikolas Olsens, 1844 (Mapcase-folder 1)
    - Title page describing the four maps in Icelandic and French), 1844 (Mapcase-folder 1)
    - No. 1, Map of Iceland (Ísland: Suðvestr - Fjórðúngr), 1844 (Mapcase-folder 1)
    - No. 2, Map of Iceland (Ísland: Suðaustr - Fjórðúngr), 1844 (Mapcase-folder 1)
    - No. 3, Map of Iceland (Ísland: Norðaustr - Fjórðúngr), 1844 (Mapcase-folder 1)
    - No. 4, Map of Iceland (Ísland: Norðvestr - Fjórðúngr), 1844 (Mapcase-folder 1)